(METAL ELEVATOR DOOR CLOSING)
(ELEVATOR ASCENDING)
(ELEVATOR CREAKING)
(GASPING)
(COUGHING)
(PANTING)
Hello?
(COUGHING)
(SQUEALING)
(LOW GROWLING)
(SNARLS)
(GASPS)
Hey! Hey! Help me!
(ELEVATOR ACCELERATING)
(PANTING)
(BUZZER SOUNDING)
(PANTING CONTINUES)
(ALL LAUGHING)
Go get him.
Day one, Greenie.
Rise and shine.
(BOY LAUGHING)
He looks like
a slopper to me.
(ALL CHATTERING)
I could use some
help in the kitchen.
(BOYS LAUGHING AND CHATTERING)
(GRUNTING)
BOYS: (SHOUTING) Oh!
Hey, we got a runner!
(PANTING)
(GROANS)
BOYS: Oh!
(ALL LAUGHING)
(BOY WHOOPING)
BOY 1: Take it all in.
(BOYS CHEERING AND APPLAUDING)
(GASPS)
(GRUNTING)
(LOCKS DOOR)
BOY: He's all yours.
Hey.
(GASPS)
Hey there, Green Bean.
You're not gonna
run again. Okay?
Good.
(UNLOCKS DOOR)
(CLEARS THROAT)
My name is Alby.
Can you tell me anything
about yourself?
Who you are?
Where you came from?
Anything at all.
No.
Can you tell
me your name?
I, uh, I can't
remember anything.
Why can't
I remember anything?
It's okay.
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
Hey, relax.
Relax.
It's normal.
(EXHALES DEEPLY)
It happens to us all.
You'll get your name
back in a day or two.
It's the one thing
they let us keep.
What is this place?
Let me show you.
(INDISTINCT CONVERSATIONS)
ALBY: We eat here.
We sleep here.
We grow
our own food.
We build
our own shelter.
Whatever we need,
the Box provides.
The rest
is up to us.
The Box?
Yeah. It's sent up
once a month
with fresh supplies
and a new Greenie.
This month
that's you.
Congratulations.
Sent up?
By who, though?
Who put us here?
That, we don't know.
Hey, are you
all right, Alby?
A-ha!
Green Bean,
meet Newt.
When I'm not around,
he's in charge.
Well, it's a good thing
you're always around then.
That was some dash
you made earlier.
For a second,
I thought you had the
chops to be a runner...
...till you
face-planted.
(LAUGHS)
That was great.
Wait, a "runner"?
Newt, do me a favor.
Go find Chuck.
All right.
Thanks.
Look, I'm sorry
to rush this.
You came up a little late,
and there's a lot to do.
We got something special
planned tonight.
Yeah. You'll see.
I hope you're not
afraid of heights.
Let's go. Come on.
This is
all we got.
We've worked
hard for it.
If you respect
this place...
you and I will
get along just fine.
What's out there?
We only have
three rules.
First, do your part.
No time for
any freeloaders.
Second, never
harm another Glader.
None of this works
unless we have trust.
Most importantly...
never go beyond
those walls.
Do you understand
me, Greenie?
CHUCK: Hey, Alby!
Hey, Chuck.
Where you been, man?
It's basically the same
story for all of us.
We wake up in the Box,
Alby gives us the tour...
then here we are.
Don't worry.
You're already
doing better than I did.
I clunked
my pants three times
before they got
me out of the pit.
No, come on.
Dude, where
are you going?
I just wanna see.
You can look
around all you want
but you better
not go out there.
Why not?
What's through there?
I don't know.
I just know
what I'm told.
And we're not
supposed to leave.
(SIGHS)
BEN: Hey, Chuck.
New Greenie, huh?
How does it feel
to be promoted?
Feels great, Ben.
I thought no one
was allowed to leave.
I said we're not
allowed to leave.
They're different,
they're runners.
They know more about
the maze than anyone.
Wait, what?
What?
What? You just
said "maze."
I did?
Yeah.
Where are you going?
What are you doing?
I'm just gonna
take a look.
I told you,
you can't.
No one leaves,
especially not now.
It's not safe.
Okay, all right,
I'm not gonna go.
Hey!
(GRUNTS)
(WHIMPERS)
We gotta
stop meeting
like this, Greenie.
Get off me!
All right!
Calm, calm, calm.
BOY: Don't touch me!
GALLY: Whoa! Take it easy!
Just relax.
What the hell is
wrong with you guys?
Just calm down,
all right?
No, okay?
Why won't you tell
me what's out there?
We're just
trying to protect you.
It's for your own good.
You guys can't
just keep me here.
I can't let you leave.
Why not?
(FAINT CLICK)
(HEAVY THUD)
(WIND WHOOSHING)
(PANTING)
What the hell?
(GEARS TURNING)
Next time,
I'm gonna
let you leave.
Welcome to the Glade.
(DRUMS PLAYING)
Light him up!
(ALL CHEERING)
(WHOOPING)
(LAUGHS)
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING)
Hell of a
first day, Greenie.
Here.
Put some hair
on your chest.
(SPITS) Oh!
(LAUGHS)
(COUGHING)
Oh, my God!
What is that?
(CONTINUES COUGHING)
I don't
even know.
It's Gally's recipe.
It's a trade secret.
(BOYS SHOUTING)
Yeah, well,
he's still an asshole.
He saved
your life today.
Trust me. The maze
is a dangerous place.
We're trapped here,
aren't we?
For the moment.
But...
you see those guys?
There, by the fire?
Those are the runners.
That guy in the middle
there, that's Minho.
He's the Keeper
of the Runners.
Every morning,
when those doors open,
they run the maze...
mapping it,
memorizing it,
trying to
find a way out.
How long have
they been looking?
Three years.
And they haven't
found anything?
It's a lot
easier said than done.
Listen.
(DISTANT CREAKING)
Hear that?
It's the maze,
changing.
It changes
every night.
How is that
even possible?
You can ask the people
who put us in here,
if you ever
meet the bastards.
Listen,
the truth is...
the runners
are the only ones
who really know
what's out there.
They are the
strongest and the
fastest of us all.
And it's a good
thing, too...
because if they
don't make it back before
those doors close...
then they are
stuck out there
for the night.
And no one
has ever survived
a night in the maze.
What happens
to them?
Well, we call
them Grievers.
Of course, no one's
ever seen one
and lived to
tell about it.
But they're out there.
Right, that's enough
questions for one night.
Come on.
You're supposed to
be the guest of honor.
Oh, no...
No! No, come on.
Let me show you around.
Come on.
(GRUNTING)
ALL: (CHEERING)
Whoa!
And there
we got the builders.
They're very good
with their hands...
but not a lot
going on upstairs.
And then
we got Winston...
he's the Keeper
of the Slicers.
And we got
two med-jacks,
Clint and Jeff.
Hey, what's up?
Yo, Newt.
They spend most
of their time bandaging
up the slicers.
What if I want
to be a runner?
(CHUCKLES)
Have you listened to
a word I've just said?
No one wants
to be a runner.
And, besides,
you gotta get chosen.
Chosen by who?
(GROANS)
BOYS: Whoa!
What do you
say, Greenie?
Wanna see what
you're made of?
(ALL CHANTING)
Greenie! Greenie! Greenie!
(CHANTING CONTINUES)
(ALL CHEERING)
Okay. All right.
The rules are
simple, Greenie.
I try to push you
out of the circle...
you try to last more
than five seconds.
(ALL LAUGHING)
BOY 1: Take it
easy on the Greenie.
GALLY: Ready?
(GRUNTING)
(BOYS SHOUTING)
(COUGHS)
BOY 2: Get up, boy.
Come on, Greenie.
We're not done yet.
Stop calling me Greenie.
GALLY:
Stop calling you that?
What do you wanna
be called? Shank?
(BOYS LAUGHING AND CHEERING)
What do you
think, boys?
Does he look
like a Shank?
(BOTH GRUNTING)
BOYS: Whoa!
BOY 3: Come on!
You know what?
I think I've settled
on Shank.
(BOYS LAUGHING)
BOYS: Oh!
There you go,
Greenie!
Not bad for
a Greenie, huh?
Oh! (COUGHS)
(BOYS CHATTERING)
Thomas.
Thomas. Hey!
Thomas!
(THOMAS LAUGHS)
I remember my name.
I'm Thomas!
ALL: Thomas!
(ALL CHEERING)
Welcome home, Thomas.
(INAUDIBLE)
Good job... Thomas.
(DISTANT ROARING)
What the hell
was that?
That, my friend,
was a Griever.
Don't worry,
you're safe
here with us.
Nothing gets
through those walls.
All right, guys.
Let's tuck it in for
the night. Come on.
It was a good night.
Good job, man.
GALLY:
You're safe here with us.
WOMAN: Wicked is good.
THOMAS: What's out there?
GIRL: Thomas, Thomas.
Can you hear me?
Everything is going to change.
ALBY: Thomas.
Shh.
Follow me.
ALBY: It's peaceful, isn't it?
I know it's hard to believe,
but it wasn't always this way.
We had dark days.
We lost a lot of boys to fear.
To panic.
We've come
far since then.
Established
order...
made peace.
Yeah. Why are
you telling me this?
Because you're not
like the others.
You're curious.
But you're
one of us now.
You need to know
what that means.
What happened
to them?
Like I said...
dark days,
Thomas.
Has anyone tried
climbing to the top?
Tried it. The ivy
doesn't go all
the way to the top.
And besides,
where are you gonna
go from there?
And what
about the Box?
You know, next
time it comes up...
No, we tried that.
The Box won't
go back down with
someone in it.
Okay, what if we...
No, we tried it,
all right?
Twice.
All right? Trust me.
Anything you think of,
we've already tried.
The only way
out of here is
through the maze.
Now, look,
you wanna be helpful?
Here.
Go dig us up
some more fertilizer.
"Just get the fertilizer,
Thomas."
"Are you sure, guys?
I can't help in
any other way?"
"No, just get
the fertilizer.
"You know where it is.
It's just out in the
middle of the woods."
(FLIES BUZZING)
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
Oh!
Uh...
You're Ben, right?
I don't know
if we ever...
(GRUNTING)
Are you okay?
(SHOUTS)
(GROANS)
Get the hell off me!
It's your fault.
I saw you.
You did this.
I saw you!
(BOTH GRUNTING)
(SCREAMS)
(CHOKING)
(GASPING)
Hey! Hey!
THOMAS: Hey!
Help!
Help! Help!
I'll kill you!
(BOYS SHOUTING)
(SCREAMS)
NEWT: Hey!
Hold him down.
What are you doing?
(GRUNTING)
Calm down, Ben.
What the hell happened?
He just attacked me!
Are you okay?
(MOANING)
GALLY: Calm down, Ben.
No. No.
All right,
lift his shirt.
Lift his shirt.
(GROANING) No! No!
No! No!
Please. Please.
(BEN PANTING)
He's been stung.
In the middle
of the day?
Help me, please.
(CRYING) Please.
Please, just help.
(SIGHS)
Put him in the pit.
GALLY: Everybody, help.
Take him to the pit.
No!
Med-jack!
Please don't do it!
Calm down, Ben.
Back down, Ben.
Listen to me! Please!
(BEN SCREAMING)
Please, stop, please!
He did this!
Please stop! No!
No, please! Help me!
THOMAS:
So what happened to him?
It's called
"The Changing."
It's what happens
when someone gets stung.
Listen.
We haven't been able
to get a clear word
out of Ben
since it happened.
He's not making
any sense.
And it's only
gonna get worse.
The infection
is spreading.
He's dangerous.
What did
he say to you?
He said he saw me...
and that this
was all my fault.
How could this
be my fault?
Get some rest.
Alby?
Yeah.
What's gonna
happen to him?
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
Just listen to me.
Just, please, listen to me!
Please, Minho!
(GROWLING)
Alby!
(BEN CONTINUES GROWLING)
(WHEEZING)
(SOBBING)
(COUGHING)
No, please.
Please, don't.
Please, don't do it.
(BEN SOBBING)
(GEARS TURNING)
(WIND WHOOSHING)
(WHIMPERING)
Poles!
(GROWLING)
Move in!
No, no, no! Please!
No, please!
Please, don't!
I can get better!
Please, just listen to me!
Please, stop, please!
ALBY: Push him in!
Stop!
(BEN CRYING)
I'll get better!
(BOYS GRUNTING)
(WHIMPERING)
(SOBBING)
(PLEADING)
(SCREAMING)
He belongs
to the maze now.
THOMAS:
Do you think he might make it?
Ben?
No.
No one survives
a night in the maze.
We just gotta
forget about him.
GIRL: Thomas.
WOMAN: Wicked is good.
Don't make it easy on them.
GIRL: Thomas.
Everything is going to change.
THOMAS: Wicked is good.
MALE SCIENTIST:
This is gonna hurt a little.
WOMAN: Wicked is good.
Thomas, you have to choose.
(GEARS TURNING)
THOMAS:
But why would Alby
go into the maze?
I mean,
he's not a runner.
NEWT: Things
are different now.
Alby went to
retrace Ben's footsteps
before sundown.
Are you gonna help?
So he's gonna
go back to where
Ben was just stung...
Alby knows
what he's doing...
all right?
He knows better
than any of us.
What does
that mean?
Well, it's like
you have heard, yeah?
Every month,
the Box sends
up a new arrival.
But someone had
to be first, right?
Someone had to have
spent a whole month
in the Glade, alone.
That was Alby.
I mean,
it can't have been easy.
But when those
other boys started
coming up,
one after the other...
he saw the truth.
And he learned
that the most
important thing...
is that we all
have each other.
Because we're all
in this together.
Yeah.
There you go,
Greenie.
(THUNDER RUMBLING)
THOMAS:
They should be back by now.
What happens if
they don't make it?
They're gonna
make it.
What happens
if they don't?
They're gonna
make it.
Come on, guys,
can't we send
someone after them?
GALLY:
That's against the rules.
Either they make it
back or they don't.
We can't risk
losing anyone else.
(WIND WHOOSHING)
Oh, no.
(BOYS MURMURING)
There!
(MINHO GRUNTING LOUDLY)
Wait,
something's wrong.
(GRUNTING)
Come on, Minho,
you can do it!
ALL: Come on! Go!
CHUCK: Come on,
you can make it!
Minho, you gotta
leave him!
They're not
gonna make it.
(BOYS SHOUTING)
You gotta
leave him!
(YELLING)
(INAUDIBLE)
CHUCK: Thomas, no!
(THOMAS GRUNTING)
(BOYS SHOUTING)
(PANTING)
Good job.
You just
killed yourself.
What?
(PANTING)
What happened
to him?
What does it
look like?
He got stung.
What happened
to his head?
I did what
I had to do.
(DISTANT ROARING)
(GRUNTING)
Okay. Okay,
help me get him up.
We gotta go.
The maze is
already changing.
Hey, Minho!
We can't just
leave him here.
THOMAS: We gotta get him up.
(BOTH GRUNTING)
Come on.
Just sit him down.
Sit him down.
(DISTANT ROARING)
This isn't going to work.
We gotta go.
We gotta go!
Wait,
what are you talking about?
We gotta hide him.
Where?
I don't know.
Are you telling me
there's not a single place
we could take him?
(GRUNTS IN FRUSTRATION)
Listen to me,
shuck-face, all right.
Take a look around.
There's nowhere to go!
(BOTH PANTING)
You don't get it.
We're already dead.
(GRUNTING)
Two, three...
(BOTH GRUNTING)
Okay.
(MAZE WALLS SHIFTING)
What are you doing?
We gotta go.
We gotta go now!
No, no, just a little more
and we'll tie it off.
(GROWLING)
Minho, stay with me.
(YELPS)
Stay with me, Minho.
Just a little more,
we're almost there.
I'm sorry, Greenie.
What?
Minho! (YELPING)
(DISTANT ROARING)
(WHIMPERS)
(GRUNTING)
(SCUTTLING)
(ROARING)
(GASPING)
Okay.
(GRUNTING)
Come on.
(PANTING)
(CREATURE RETREATING)
(WALLS SHIFTING)
(DISTANT ROARING)
(SQUISHES)
Whoa!
(SCREAMS)
(ROARS)
(PANTING)
Oh!
Oh, shit!
(SCREAMS)
Whoa!
(PANTING)
(ROARING)
(YELLS)
(GRUNTING)
(SCREAMING)
(GROANS)
(GASPS)
You're a crazy
son of a bitch.
Come on, follow me.
Come on!
(BOTH PANTING)
(WALLS SHIFTING)
Okay, it's changing.
Come on, come on!
This section
is closing.
Come on.
We can lose
it down here!
Thomas!
What are you waiting for?
Get out of there!
(ROARING)
Come on!
Come on, Thomas!
Don't look back!
Run!
(SCREAMS)
Move it, Thomas! Go on!
Move your ass!
Let's go! Come on!
Come on, Greenie!
Let's go!
Thomas!
Guys, get up!
I told you, Chuck.
They're not coming back.
BOY: Let's go.
No way.
Yeah!
Yes!
(BOYS EXCLAIMING IN SURPRISE)
I got him,
I got him, I got him.
Watch out. Easy.
What happened out there?
How did you guys make it out?
You saw a Griever?
Yeah, I saw one.
He didn't just see it.
He killed it.
(BOYS CHATTERING EXCITEDLY)
Things are changing.
(BOYS SHUSHING)
There's no denying that.
First, Ben gets
stung in broad daylight.
And then Alby.
And now our Greenie, here,
has taken it upon himself...
to go into the maze.
Which is a
clear violation of
our rules here.
Yeah...
but he saved Alby's life.
Did he?
For 3 years,
we have coexisted
with these things.
And now, you've killed
one of them.
Who knows what that
could mean for us.
What do you
suggest we do?
He has to
be punished.
(BOYS PROTESTING)
Come on.
He killed a Griever!
Minho.
You were there with him.
What do you think?
I think...
in all the time
we've been here...
no one has ever
killed a Griever before.
When I turned
tail and ran...
this dumb shank stayed
behind to help Alby.
Look, I don't know
if he's brave or stupid.
But whatever it is,
we need more of it.
I say we make
him a runner.
FRY: A runner? What?
(BOYS CHATTERING)
Minho, let's not
jump the gun, here.
Thomas! Thomas! Thomas!
If you want to throw
the newbie a parade,
that's fine.
Go ahead.
But if there is one thing
I know about the maze...
it is that you do not...
(BOYS SHOUTING)
Okay, wait.
I know that sound.
The Box.
It's coming back up.
It shouldn't be.
(SHOUTING CONTINUES)
FRY:
Newt, what do you see?
BOY 1: Do you see it?
It's a girl.
(BOYS EXCLAIMING IN SURPRISE)
BOY 2: No way.
NEWT: I think she's dead.
What's in her hand?
"She's the
last one... ever."
What the hell
does that mean?
(GASPING)
ALL: Whoa!
(PANTING)
Thomas...
Do you still think
I'm overreacting?
(ALBY BREATHING HEAVILY)
NEWT:
Jeff, what's going on?
What's the matter with her?
Why won't she wake up?
Hey man, I got my job
the same way you did.
Do you
recognize her?
No.
Really? Because
she seemed to
recognize you.
What about
the note?
We'll worry
about the note later.
I think you should
worry about it now.
We've got enough to
deal with at the moment.
He's right, Newt.
If the Box isn't
coming back up,
how long do you
think we can last?
No one said that.
Let's not jump
to any conclusions.
We'll just wait
until she wakes up
and see what she knows.
Somebody has gotta have
some answers around here.
Okay.
Where are you going?
Back into the maze.
Hey.
Hey, Thomas.
What is this with you, huh?
A death wish?
You just got out and
now you want back in?
(SIGHS)
Newt said that no one
has ever seen a Griever
and lived to tell
about it, right?
Minho, now we have one.
You're telling me
you're not even
a little bit curious?
Not really, no.
So, what's the plan?
You're gonna go out
and dissect that
thing all by yourself?
I will if I have to.
Have the other
runners left yet?
The other runners
quit this morning.
(SIGHS) After Alby
got stung, they're not
in any hurry to
get back out there.
Why are you?
I think it's time
we find out what
we're really up against.
All right.
But you're not going
back out there alone.
Meet me in the woods
in half-an-hour.
(EXHALES)
Will this be enough?
Okay.
Let's go.
Come on!
That's disgusting.
There's something
in there.
You mean, besides
a Griever pancake?
Whoa, what are
you doing?
ALL: Whoa!
I thought you
said it was dead.
Was it a reflex?
You hope.
Okay, come on.
Let's try and
pull it out.
Everyone get
a hand on it.
Come on.
All right, ready?
On three.
One, two, three!
(ALL GRUNTING)
(ALL PANTING)
Are you okay, Fry?
Yeah. Thanks, brother.
(BOYS GROANING IN DISGUST)
What the hell is that?
Interesting.
FRY:
Okay, whatever it is...
can we take this up
back at the Glade?
Because I don't
want to meet
this guy's friends.
He's right.
It's getting late.
Come on.
THOMAS: We found this.
It was inside a Griever.
These are the same letters
we get in our supplies.
Yeah.
Whoever put us
here obviously
made the Grievers.
This is the
first real clue,
the first anything,
you've found in
over 3 years.
Right, Minho?
Right.
THOMAS: Newt, we gotta
go back out there.
Who knows where
this might lead us.
You see what he's
trying to do, right?
First he breaks
our rules...
and then he
tries to convince us
to abandon them totally.
The rules are the only
thing that have ever
held us together.
Why now are we
questioning that?
If Alby was here,
you know he'd
agree with me.
This shank needs
to be punished.
You're right.
Thomas broke the rules.
One night in the pit,
and no food.
Come on, Newt!
One night in the pit?
Do you think
that's gonna stop him
from going into the maze?
No.
And we can't just
have non-runners
running into the maze
whenever they feel like it.
So let's just
make this official.
Starting from tomorrow,
you're a runner.
Wow.
Gally...
No, Fry.
Thanks, Newt.
Hey, where
are we going?
You'll see.
(SIGHS)
It's the maze.
All of it.
What do you mean "all of it"?
I thought you were
still mapping it.
There's nothing
left to map.
I've run every
inch of it myself.
Every cycle.
Every pattern.
If there was
a way out,
we would have
found it by now.
Why haven't you
told anyone this?
It was Alby's call.
People needed to
believe we had a chance
of getting out.
But maybe now...
we have a real chance.
(SIGHS)
Take a look at this.
About a year ago,
we started exploring
these outer sections.
We found these numbers
printed on the walls.
Sections 1 through 8.
See, the way it works,
is every night,
when the maze changes...
it opens up
a new section.
So today,
Section 6 was open.
Tomorrow, it will be 4,
then 8, then 3.
The pattern
always stays the same.
What's so
special about 7?
I don't know.
But last night,
when you killed
that Griever...
Section 7 was open.
I think it must be
where it comes from.
Tomorrow,
you and I are gonna
take a closer look.
Hey!
What are you guys doing?
You're not allowed in here.
(PANTING)
Sorry, it's just
the, uh...
It's the girl.
Is she awake?
You could
say that.
Chuck,
what's going on?
(LAUGHING)
Girls are awesome.
(BOYS CLAMORING)
GIRL: Leave me alone!
FRY: Watch your head!
(BOYS SHOUTING)
Hey, throw one more
of those things... Ow!
Go away!
We come in peace!
What happened?
Just duck!
I don't think she
likes us very much.
GIRL: What do you
want from me?
We just wanna talk.
I'm warning you!
Take cover, y'all!
Take cover!
(ALL SHOUTING)
Hey, it's Thomas!
It's Thomas!
I'm gonna
come up, okay?
Okay.
Just me.
I'm coming up.
(BOYS CHATTERING)
Whoa, whoa, whoa.
Okay, just...
Easy, all right?
Where am I?
What is this place?
Why can't
I remember
anything?
This is all normal. Okay?
We've all been through this.
Okay?
Your name will
come back to you
in a couple of days.
It's the one
thing that...
Teresa.
What did you say?
My name.
It's Teresa.
Teresa, I'm Thomas.
But you already knew that,
though, I guess, huh?
They said I kept saying
your name in my sleep.
Who are you?
I don't know.
(STAMMERING)
I can't remember.
None of us here can
remember anything.
We all woke up here
just like you did.
Hey, I promise...
I'm gonna take this.
Okay. (SIGHS)
GALLY:
What's going on up there?
Is she coming down?
Um...
Hey, listen, you guys just
give us a second, okay?
All right.
Come on.
Is this what all
girls are like?
ZART: That girl is crazy.
"She's the last one."
What does that mean?
I'm not sure.
Ever since
you came up,
that Box hasn't
gone back down.
I just think
it's got everyone
a little worried.
Especially Gally.
He thinks
it's my fault.
Are you sure you don't
remember anything else?
I remember water...
feeling like
I was drowning.
These faces
staring at me.
And this woman's voice
saying the same
thing over and over.
"Wicked is good."
Ever since I've been here,
I've had these dreams.
Well, I thought
they were dreams.
You...
You were there.
You were there...
and you told me
that everything
was gonna change.
What does it mean?
I don't know.
I just always get pieces.
And the others don't
remember anything?
No.
Why are we different?
These were in my
pocket when I came up.
"W.C. K. D."
"Wicked is good."
What if we were
sent here for a reason?
Alby.
(GROANING SOFTLY)
NEWT: We don't even
know what this stuff is.
We don't know
who sent it.
Or why it came
up here with you.
For all we know,
this thing
could kill him.
He's already dying.
Look at him.
How could
this possibly make
it any worse?
(CONTINUES GROANING)
Come on,
it's worth a try.
All right.
Do it.
Okay.
(GASPS)
You shouldn't be here!
No!
Watch out!
(GRUNTING)
Get the syringe! Let go!
(BOTH PANTING)
Well, that worked.
Okay, from now on...
someone stays here
and watches him
around the clock.
Hey.
Sundown, Greenie.
Time to go.
Hey, what is your
problem with me?
Everything started
going wrong the minute
you showed up.
First Ben, then Alby...
and now the girl.
Everybody saw
she recognized you.
And I'm betting
you know who she is.
(SIGHS)
Gally...
you know we can't
stay here forever,
right?
(RUSTLING)
Who's there?
It's just me.
Sorry, Chuck.
Here.
You'll run better
on a full stomach.
Mmm...
Thanks, Chuck.
Hey, what do
you got there?
Wow, that came out
pretty damn good.
What's that for?
It's for my parents.
You remember
your parents?
No.
I mean, I know
I must have them.
(SIGHS)
And wherever they are,
I'm sure they miss me...
but I can't miss
them because I don't
remember them.
What do you think
you're gonna find
out there tomorrow?
Uh, I don't know.
But if there's
a way out, Chuck,
me and Minho
are gonna find it.
(SIGHS)
Here.
Chuck, why would
you give this to me?
I can't remember
them anyway.
But maybe if you
find a way out,
you can give it
to them for me.
I'll let you
get some sleep.
Hey, Chuck.
Come here.
Put out your hand.
I want you to give
that to them yourself.
We're gonna
get out of here.
All of us.
Okay?
I promise.
Yeah.
All right.
Good night.
Good night, buddy.
(SIGHS)
Big day, Greenie.
Are you sure
you don't wanna
sit this one out?
Come on, man.
Get me out of here.
All right.
(DOOR OPENING)
Let's go!
(PANTING)
This way.
Not much further to
the inner ring.
Let's go!
Come on! This way.
(BOTH PANTING)
MINHO: That's strange.
THOMAS: What?
Seven is not
supposed to be open
for another week.
THOMAS: What the
hell is this place?
MINHO:
We call them blades.
It's Ben's, isn't it?
Yeah.
A Griever must have
pulled him down here.
(DEVICE POWERING UP)
Whoa, hey!
(DEVICE CLICKING)
(DEVICE BEEPING)
I think it's
showing us the way.
Wait, wait, wait.
What, what?
(BEEPING RAPIDLY)
This way. Come on.
(BEEPING INTENSIFIES)
Minho, you ever see
this place before?
No.
(BEEPING ACCELERATES)
(EXCLAIMS)
It's just another
dead end.
(DOOR OPENING)
Are you sure
about this?
Nope.
Grievers.
(BUZZING)
(BEEPING)
What the
hell was that?
(ALARM BLARING)
We gotta
get out of here.
Give me the key,
give me the key!
(GASPS)
Move, move!
(BOTH PANTING)
We gotta go!
Run, Thomas!
We're gonna
get trapped!
Go! Go!
(YELLING)
MINHO: Go, go, go!
(CONTINUES YELLING)
Move!
(SHOUTS)
(BOTH PANTING HEAVILY)
Minho!
MINHO: Come on!
Let's go, let's go!
(BOTH YELLING)
Come on, move!
Keep going!
Keep going! Let's go!
BOTH: Whoa!
Go, go, go!
(BOTH PANTING HEAVILY)
Oh!
Go, go, go!
BOTH: Whoa!
Come on!
Don't look back!
(THOMAS YELLS)
Oh, shit!
There!
Whoa, whoa, whoa!
(BOTH GRUNTING)
(GROANING)
Oh!
NEWT: What the hell's
going on out there?
What the hell you
done now, Thomas?
We found something,
a new passage.
We think it
could be a way out.
Really?
It's true.
We opened a door,
something I'd
never seen before.
I think it must be
where the Grievers
go during the day.
Wait! Whoa, whoa, whoa...
You're saying you found
the Grievers' home?
And you want
us to go in?
Their way in could
be our way out, Chuck.
Yeah, or there could
be a dozen Grievers
on the other side.
The truth is,
Thomas doesn't know
what he has done, as usual.
Yeah, at least
I did something,
Gally.
I mean, what
have you done?
Aside from hide
behind these walls
all the time?
Let me tell you
something, Greenie.
You've been here
3 days, all right?
I've been here 3 years!
Yeah, you've been
here 3 years and you're
still here, Gally!
What does
that tell you?
Maybe you should
start doing things
a little differently.
Maybe you should
be in charge,
what about that?
Hey, it's Alby!
He's awake.
Has he said anything?
No.
Alby...
Alby, are you all right?
Hey, Alby.
Alby, we might
have just found a way
out of the maze.
Do you hear me?
We could be
getting out of here.
We can't.
We can't leave.
They won't let us.
What are you
talking about?
I remember.
What do
you remember?
You.
You were always
their favorite, Thomas.
Always.
(BOYS SHOUTING)
Why did you do this?
Why did you come here?
(SHOUTING CONTINUES)
(CRYING)
Winston,
what's going on?
It's the doors.
They aren't closing.
(BOYS SHOUTING)
(LOUD CLANG)
(ALL GROAN)
(BOYS SHOUTING)
Chuck, go to
the Council Hall
and start barricading
the doors.
Mmm-hmm.
Winston,
you go with him.
Got it.
Get the others.
Tell them to go to the forest.
Go hide, now!
Minho, I want you to grab
every weapon you can find.
I'll meet you
at Council Hall.
Let's go.
Teresa, you and I
are gonna go get Alby,
all right? Come on.
(BOYS SHOUTING
IN THE DISTANCE)
(ROARING)
All right, everybody hide!
Teresa!
Come on! Run! Run!
(BOYS SCREAMING
IN THE DISTANCE)
Stay down!
BOY 1: Run!
(GRIEVER GROWLING)
(BOY 2 SCREAMS)
(BOY 3 SCREAMS)
(BOYS SCREAMING IN DISTANCE)
Ahh!
Zart!
(SCREAMING)
ZART: Help me!
Go! Get to the village!
Go, go, go!
(ZART CONTINUES SCREAMING)
(SHUSHING)
Stay down,
stay down!
Gally! Let me in,
let me in!
(SCREAMS)
THOMAS: Alby!
TERESA: Are you okay?
What's going on?
They're here.
Grievers?
(BOY SCREAMING)
Thomas,
what do we do?
It's got me!
(SCREAMING)
(GRIEVER SNARLING)
Everybody, run, run, run!
Jeff, come on, go, go, go!
(ALL SHOUTING)
(YELLS)
(SCREECHING)
Everyone,
go, go, go!
(SCREAMS)
Keep moving!
Oh, shit!
Ahh!
JEFF: Alby!
Get behind me!
Come on!
FRY:
Over here, let's go!
Over here!
Let's go! Come on!
Over here, come on!
Winston!
Get Alby inside.
Chuck, get in! Go, go, go!
Lock down the doors!
(GRIEVER GROWLING)
(POUNDING ON DOOR)
TERESA: Careful.
(GRIEVER SNARLING)
ALL: Whoa!
NEWT: Stay back, guys.
(GRIEVER SCUTTLING ON ROOF)
(TERESA SHUSHING)
(ALL SCREAMING)
(ALL GROANING)
(ALL COUGHING)
NEWT: Is everyone all right?
BOY: Help!
Hey, grab him!
Help!
(ALL EXCLAIMING)
Watch out!
(GRIEVER GROWLING)
(ALL SCREAMING)
JEFF: Chuck!
(SCREAMS)
Chuck, no!
THOMAS: Grab him!
Pull him back!
(ALL GRUNTING)
CHUCK: Help!
Chuck, don't let go!
No shit!
TERESA: Pull!
NEWT: Don't let him go!
(ALL GRUNTING)
(YELLING)
(CONTINUES YELLING)
(CHUCK COUGHING)
Chuck, are you okay?
Yeah, I'm fine.
Thanks, Alby.
Alby! Watch out!
(GROANS)
(ALL SHOUTING)
NEWT: Grab him!
(GRUNTING)
Thomas, get them out.
(SCREAMS)
Alby!
No!
TERESA: Thomas...
Thomas!
CHUCK: Don't go out there!
MINHO: No, Thomas, wait!
Thomas, wait!
(GRIEVERS ROARING
IN THE DISTANCE)
(BOYS SCREAMING
BOY: Where is everybody?
Who's that over there?
Gally... (GROANS)
(ALL PROTESTING)
This is all you, Thomas!
Look around!
MINHO: Back off, Gally!
It's not Thomas' fault!
GALLY: You heard
what Alby said!
He's one of them!
NEWT: One of who?
He's one of them,
and they sent him here
to destroy everything,
and now he has!
Look around, Thomas!
Look around!
This is your fault!
MINHO: Back off, Gally!
This is not Thomas' fault!
NEWT: What are you
talking about?
Calm down.
GALLY: They sent him here,
and now he's destroyed
everything that we've built!
NEWT: What are you
talking about?
(BOYS ARGUING)
Maybe he's right.
Thomas...
THOMAS: I need
to remember, Teresa.
Thomas...
Thomas!
No, don't!
(GROANING)
Thomas!
Chuck, get
the other syringe!
It's okay.
Thomas, I'm here.
THOMAS: Who put us here?
ALBY: That we don't know.
THOMAS: Teresa...
why are we doing this?
WOMAN: Excellent, Thomas.
Come with me.
Wicked isn't good.
WOMAN: Thomas...
Wicked is good.
THOMAS: How could
this be my fault?
BEN: You did this!
I saw you!
THOMAS: I can't keep
watching them die.
TERESA: Hey.
Are you okay?
What the hell
were you thinking?
What happened?
NEWT: Gally
has taken control.
He said we had a choice.
Either join him...
or get banished
at sundown with you.
(GROANS) And the others
agreed to that?
Gally has everyone
convinced that
you're the reason
all this has happened.
Well, he's been
right so far.
What are you
talking about?
This place...
it's not what
we thought it was.
It's not a prison,
it's a test.
It all started
when we were kids.
They would give us
these challenges.
They were experimenting
on us.
And then people
started disappearing.
Every month,
one after the other,
like clockwork.
They were sending
them up into the maze.
Yeah, but not all of us.
What do you mean?
Guys, I'm one of them.
The people
who put you here,
I worked with them.
I watched
you guys for years.
The entire time
you have been here...
I was on the other
side of it.
So were you.
What?
Teresa, we did this
to them.
No.
That can't be true.
THOMAS: It is. I saw it.
Why would they send us
up if we were with them?
It doesn't matter.
NEWT: He's right.
Any of it.
Because the people
we were before the maze
don't even exist anymore.
These Creators
took care of that.
But what does matter
is who we are now,
and what we do...
right now.
You went into the maze
and you found a way out.
Yeah, but if I hadn't,
Alby would still be alive.
Maybe.
But I know that
if he were here,
he would be telling you
the exact same thing.
Pick your ass up
and finish what you started.
Because if we do nothing...
then that means
Alby died for nothing,
and I can't have that.
Okay.
Okay, but we gotta
get through Gally first.
This is such a waste.
Gally...
It doesn't feel
right, man.
JEFF: Yeah, what if
Thomas is right?
Maybe he can
lead us home.
We are home.
Okay?
I don't wanna
have to cross any more
names off that wall.
You really think
banishing us
is gonna solve
anything?
No.
But this isn't
a banishing.
It's an offering.
What? Wait!
Gally, what are you doing?
You really think
I'm gonna let Thomas
back into the maze
after what he has done?
Look around you!
Look at our Glade!
This is the only way.
And when the Grievers get
what they came here for...
everything goes back
to the way it was.
Are you listening
to this?
Why are you all
just standing there?
He's crazy!
You shut up.
If you stay here,
the Grievers are
going to come back.
They're gonna come back,
and they're gonna
keep coming back...
until you're all dead!
Shut up! Tie him up!
Do you hear me?
I said tie him up!
(ALL GRUNTING)
You're full of surprises,
aren't you?
You don't have
to come with us,
but we are leaving.
Anyone else who
wants to come,
now is your last chance.
Don't listen to him,
he's just trying
to scare you.
No, I'm not trying
You're already scared.
I'm scared.
But I'd rather risk
my life out there
than spending the rest
of it in here.
We don't belong here.
This place isn't our home.
We were put here.
We were trapped here.
At least, out there
we have a choice.
We can make it
out of here.
I know that.
I'm sorry.
THOMAS: Gally, it's over.
Just come with us.
Good luck against
the Grievers.
THOMAS: Everybody,
this way!
Keep it up, guys,
we're almost there!
(GROWLING)
Is it a Griever?
Yeah.
Shit.
You take this, Chuck.
Stay behind us.
It's okay.
Just stick
with me.
Once we're through,
it will activate
and the door will open.
We stay close,
we stick together...
we get through this.
We get out now...
or we die trying.
Ready?
All right. Let's go!
(ALL YELLING)
(ROARING)
MINHO: Get up, look out!
Push it!
Look out!
(SCREAMING)
(ROARS)
(ALL GASP)
The key!
Chuck! Watch the edge!
(GRUNTING)
(SNARLING)
Oh, no.
I got you, Chuck!
Pull me up!
(ALL YELLING)
(ALL CHEERING)
TERESA: Come on!
Thomas! Thomas!
Chuck?
We got more coming!
Keep it steady, guys!
(KEY BEEPING)
It works!
(BOY SCREAMING)
Teresa, go!
THOMAS: Don't back down!
Keep pushing!
NEWT: Stay together!
(TERESA GRUNTS
IN FRUSTRATION)
There's gotta be
a way out! Come on!
(YELLS)
THOMAS: Watch it!
(SCREAMING)
(ROARING)
TERESA: It won't open!
Thomas!
There's a code!
Eight numbers!
Eight sections
of the maze.
Hey, Minho!
What's the sequence?
What?
The sections of the maze,
what's the sequence?
Seven! One!
Five! Two!
Six! Four!
Heads up!
(ROARING)
(SCREAMS)
NEWT: Minho!
THOMAS: Minho!
Oh!
(GRUNTING)
Get off of me!
(YELLS)
(GRUNTING)
(SCREAMING)
Jeff!
(CONTINUES SCREAMING)
What's the sequence?
Come on!
Six! Four! Eight!
Three! You got it?
THOMAS: Keep holding!
Almost there, come on!
BOY: The door opened!
(BOTH SCREECHING)
(BOYS SCREAMING)
(GRUNTS)
BOYS: Oh!
(ALL SIGHING IN RELIEF)
(ALL SCREAMING)
Seriously?
WINSTON: What happened here?
So they were watching us.
This whole time.
Hello.
My name is
Doctor Ava Paige.
I'm Director
of Operations
of the World Catastrophe
Killzone Department.
If you're watching this,
that means
you have successfully
completed the Maze Trials.
I wish I could
be there in person
to congratulate you...
but circumstances seem
to have prevented it.
I'm sure by now,
you must all be
very confused...
angry...
frightened.
I can only assure you,
that everything
that's happened to you...
everything we've done
to you...
it was all done
for a reason.
You won't remember...
but the Sun has
scorched our world.
Billions of lives
lost to fire...
famine...
suffering
on a global scale.
The fallout
was unimaginable.
What came after was worse.
We called it the Flare.
A deadly virus that
attacks the brain.
It is violent...
unpredictable...
incurable.
Or so we thought.
In time, a new
generation emerged
that could survive
the virus.
Suddenly, there was
a reason to hope
for a cure.
But finding it
would not be easy.
The young would
have to be tested,
even sacrificed...
inside harsh environments...
where their brain activity
could be studied.
All in an effort
to understand...
what makes them different...
what makes you different.
You may not realize it...
but you're very important.
Unfortunately, your trials
have only just begun.
As you will no doubt
soon discover,
not everyone agrees
with our methods.
Progress is slow,
people are scared.
It may be too late for us...
for me...
but not for you.
The outside world awaits.
Remember...
Wicked is good.
(GUNSHOT)
(DOOR OPENING)
Is it over?
She said we were
important.
What are we
supposed
to do now?
I don't know.
Let's get out of here.
GALLY: No.
Gally?
Don't.
He's been stung.
(SNIFFLES)
We can't leave.
We did.
Gally, we're out.
We're free.
Free?
You think we're
free out there?
No.
No, there's no escape
from this place.
Gally, listen to me.
You're not
thinking straight.
You're not.
Now, we can help you.
Just put down the gun.
I belong to the maze.
THOMAS: Just put down
the gun.
We all do.
(GALLY WHEEZING)
(KEY CLATTERING)
(GASPS)
Thomas...
Chuck.
(GROANING)
Oh, shit. Shit.
Look at me,
look at me!
Oh, shit!
(WHIMPERING)
THOMAS: Chuck,
look at me, all right?
I got you, buddy.
Just hang on.
It's okay.
Thomas, Thomas...
No, Chuck.
You're gonna give
it to them yourself.
Remember,
I told you that.
Take it.
THOMAS: No.
Thank you.
No, Chuck,
you're gonna get...
(GROANS SOFTLY)
(EXHALES)
Chuck.
Chuck? Hey.
Hey, Chuck, come on!
Come on, wake up!
(SOBBING)
THOMAS: Damn it!
(SOBBING) We made it.
Come on.
I'm sorry!
God damn it!
(DOORS OPENING)
Damn it!
(THOMAS CONTINUES SOBBING)
Thomas.
THOMAS: Chuck!
Get up, Chuck! Come on!
(HOODED MEN SHOUTING)
THOMAS: Chuck!
You can't just
leave him there!
You guys all right?
Don't worry.
You're safe now.
Relax, kid.
Everything is gonna change.
I think it's safe to say
the Maze Trials were
a complete success.
I wasn't expecting
so many survivors, but...
the more the merrier.
Thomas continues to
surprise and impress.
And for now, they seem
to have taken the bait.
It's too soon to say...
but they could be
the key to everything.
So let's move forward.
It's time now
to begin Phase Two.